[Music]
there are folks it's high time we got
into some detail about program design
and cover this fancy word people refer
to as periodization I'm gonna talk about
what periodization
is a little bit about the philosophy and
then most of the video actually I'll
spend time walking you through how I
frame writing a program in other words
how I my recommendation rata actually go
about writing your first training
program for someone all right so let's
dive into a little bit and what I think
will be another fantastic episode of
25-minute physiology I think we can do
this in 25 minutes or less so should be
fun all right when we think about the
word periodization what we're really
talking about is plan the variation in
code verb now if you have no idea what
that acronym stands for you'll have to
go back and check out one of my other
videos called the seven modifiable
variables okay but in other words
depending on how we alter volume or the
exercises or the intensity or the order
we do them in when we do we make
variations in that stuff on purpose to
get it in to elicit a very explicit and
specific adaptation that's parodies a
ssin in a nutshell right it's planned
variation now I'm underlying plan
because as wife good close friend Chris
Moore once said variation does not mean
randomization and hence the difference
between periodization and people that
don't know what the frick they're doing
okay so just doing random different
things is fine variation is important
for overall adaptation but that's not
periodization that's not even telogen
program design cuz not planned so we
don't want randomization we do want
variation but we want variation with
intent so we don't want to just randomly
change the exercises the rep ranges and
things like that we want to think
through what's happening today this week
this month this year and maybe even
these three or four years and then very
strategically select how we're going to
implement our COFA verb if we do this
thing right we should both decrease our
chances of overuse injury so we can't do
anything about acute trauma soccer
player getting kicked in the face or
something
we can't help with overuse injuries and
at this and also the other thing we can
do is peak at the right time right no
one likes being the strongest or fastest
they've ever been six days before a
competition or two days after so that's
the point of pure is a ssin to try to
figure out how we can manipulate our
programs so that we decrease our chances
of injury overuse injury and we peak at
the right time the way to do that is to
have planning planning planning planning
this is what Peter's ation cycle would
typically look at now these terms are
important for any certification or exams
you may take in my class anyway so a
macro cycle is the biggest macro means
large right so most people work on a
one-year long macro cycle if you think
about a typical sport athlete it's
almost a year-round thing now Olympic
athletes work on what we would in the
bids called a quad that's because we're
really trying to peak and maximize
performance every four years but for the
rest of video just kind of think about a
macro as one year within that macro are
a bunch of mezzos no mezzo look one of
the assignments you'll do in my class
but a mezzo means mill and so you might
have two or three or four or five
mesocycles in your macro cycle there's
no okay sorry about that
my dog's no key and Ghostface killer had
to ward off an attack from aliens or
something and got a little excited but
they should be calm down now anyways
there's no set number of meds of cycles
you have to have in a macro cycle okay
so in this example I'll show you three
or four but you could have two Meadows
in your macro where six or eight or
whatever else
now within those Meadows I like to think
about breaking those up into smaller
blocks so for example if you have a meso
cycle that's four months long it's kind
of easy to break that up into two or
four smaller blocks okay but you don't
have to do that if you've got a meso
cycle at six weeks
you don't need multiple blocks probably
one block is sufficient so in that case
you might as well you might skip that
and go straight to micro-cycles micro
meaning small it's kind of the smallest
unit of program design and that's
typically a week now some advanced
people will do like nine-day micros but
it's got
applicated so at this point is think
about it this way macros a year within
the macro you've got three or four
mesocycles that are two three four
months each within the those you've got
a couple of blocks and within all of
that you've got weeks right so if you've
got a eight week long mezzo cycle you
might have two blocks that are four
micro cycles each something like that
I've laid out a calendar here at the
bottom so you can get a good feel for
this imagine you've got a winter sport
athlete and you're playing games and
August's all the way through say
hopefully December you go into the
postseason in January in February and
that postseason would then be say a
two-month long mesocycle and will name
that mesocycle postseason mesocycle and
we might have one or two blocks in that
with our eight micro-cycles
okay but like I said the competition
season was another mezzo cycle and this
muscle is actually maybe four months
long after post season you go into a
three and a half month long offseason
program and then you've got maybe
another two months or so set aside for
pre-season so in this particular example
which is very very very very common for
most traditional athletes you've got
four mesocycles in your macro cycle all
right you know the way that you would
break that up would be something like
this in your assignment for my class and
you do this I'm gonna need to see a
schematic I in fact if you're in the
program design class specifically you
got to do this for the whole macro if
you're in the undergrad class this is
same thing for your puzzle but it would
look something like this okay and I get
eggs made this up this would be the four
mezzo example and random different sizes
and lengths of blocks this highlighting
and showing you this schematic what
would look like visually in terms of the
progression of the macro you'll notice
this is the exact opposite of exercise
order within a day so what I mean is the
very traditional macro cycle progression
is this okay do your conditioning those
types of things earlier and get an
aerobic base built at the beginning of
the year transition that into so my per
Trofim move from there to strength and
convert all that strength in his speed
and power alright so there you go
traditional periodization model if
you're taking a certification
and say okay there you go and if you ask
any athlete or if you were an athlete
you probably think yeah that's kind of
exactly what we did
ten months away from competition we did
conditioning we built the base we
transition to hypertrophy strength power
speed etc now here's the basic idea you
get into shape first why so that you can
handle the training volume that's gonna
be coming later once you do that you add
some muscle mass maybe even overshoot so
say you want to play at 200 pounds you
might bulk up to 250 in the offseason
why because you know you're not gonna do
a lot I burped Rafi in season you're
gonna lose some muscle mass possibly say
maybe overshoot a little bit you take
that all that atom muscle in your jack
City and you convert that to new mega
amounts of strength and with more force
we can hopefully move our mass better
and therefore be more powerful and then
eventually faster which most sports are
more reliant upon power and speed than
they our strength our per tripping no I
don't particularly love this progression
I think they're better ways to think
about it but I'm not gonna cover in this
video I would encourage you to check out
Brian Mackenzie's book power speed
endurance John Cronin in New Zealand has
a fantastic model as well but as a very
beginner intro philosophy this is the
basics of periodization and programs
Simon okay so how you progressively
overload or how you achieve that
overload throughout the year there's no
magic here so you could start off in
December the beginning of the year and
you're working hard for two or three
weeks and you gotta start progressing
progressively overloading you could
increase the volume by increasing the
repetitions you could do more sets you
can do more exercises you could add
frequencies so you're doing more
workouts in a week you could do any of
that or increase intensity so start
lifting a little bit heavier add five
pounds every week at 2% whatever it's
gonna be you can do the same thing and
decrease the restaurants you could start
increasing the complexity of the
exercises or any combination of these so
these are just a few examples it doesn't
and nothing it doesn't matter it does
matter but points any of it could work
so you have to progress in some fashion
as you move throughout the year that's
the most important thing
the other thing you're going to hear
commonly is we would typically move from
general to specific throughout the year
so when we're really far away from
competition we're gonna be doing more
general movement so another way to think
about this is they don't have to be
incredibly sports specific as we get
close to the competition though we do
get more specific and so I've listed six
different items here that all move from
general to specific as the season gets
closer I'm not gonna go through them all
because I'd be just kind of redundant
you'll get it you're smart I know you
are I'll just go a couple so you make
sure you understand what I'm saying take
a look at the range of motion so you may
do something like I'm working with a
basketball player and so ten months away
from season I'm not gonna do exercises
that and I make sure that they go
through the exact same range of motion
that my player goes through in a game
because I don't need to be that specific
I'll do more general kind of what I'm
getting at here is one philosophy I'm
not saying I agree with this but one
philosophy would be okay in the
offseason so after the season's over
we're gonna come and we'll do full range
of motion squatting and I know you'll
never do a full all hip flexion all the
way down to the bottom squat in a
basketball game but I don't care I want
a general movement pattern but as we get
close through the season maybe preseason
and in season we'll start transitioning
from full depth squats to partial range
of motion half squat through quarter
squat because that's more specific to
the range of motion you're gonna get in
a game so that would be one example of
moving your program from general to
specific you can do the same thing with
energy systems so I remember in college
football the first workouts we would do
after the season was over when we would
come back and we would play flag
football we would play a frisbee tagging
or we would do things like that we would
do basketball pickup games we play
things that were not the exact same
interview systems that we used in a
football game that's because we were
trying to be more broad more general but
I promise you we were not playing
grab-ass we're not playing pickup
basketball
three weeks before the season started
all of our conditioning was very
specific to not only the sport but our
position so we were staying within those
energy domains those work to rest ratios
that we're going to be experiencing in
games general to specific and you can do
the same thing for speed of movement
muscle action and probably a whole host
of everything other things I just want
give you some examples okay very common
though I got a progressively overload
somehow throughout the year and I will
typically move for more general to
specific now as the years progress as
well in your own personal training
experience you'll hedge towards more
more from one to the other what I mean
is if you have saying a high school
athlete or middle school athlete you're
probably gonna spend almost your entire
year on general as they get into high
school get into college now become pro
athletes of twenty two now we're
probably doing a little bit less general
training in more specific but we don't
want to do sports specific training only
for high school kids especially in
middle school kids that's preposterous
it's stupid we need very general
training right we're not trying to
optimize sport performance when you're
sixteen you want to make sure that you
can place them when you're 23 and they
not broken when you're 27 all right so
the style in which you get that
progression either general too specific
or that overload how you do that that's
periodization and a lot of people have
different philosophies and styles of
periodization and that all that means is
they like to increase their volume
differently or they like to increase
their intensity differently or they
progress from one type of exercise to
another different than either one so
their philosophy and that gets extremely
complicated we've got an entire class
some of you might be in right now or
some of you I want to take it next but
it is very very complicated but that's
really all it is
burgum design is their peers ation it's
just how do I progress over the course
the year so that I can argue to train
more and not be hurt now for those of
you that are new that periodization I
want to go through the basics of how the
year would look this is a very common
question on personal training or
strength coach certification so make
sure you understand the fundamentals or
the foundation of puritan so here I've
used a 12-month macro cycle and I put in
for mezzo cycles and you can see at the
end of the year we will have a certain
day that we want a peak hour performance
when people ask you about how
quote/unquote periodization works what
they're generally referring to is how do
you manipulate volume and intensity over
time and the basic answer is this volume
comes down and intensity goes up now you
don't need to memorize that because it
would not make sense at all to do the
other thing remember intensity is like
what person
my maximum lifting out what percentage
of my speed am I going in you wouldn't
want to go into competition after six
months of going slower and slower and
slower and more and more and more reps
that doesn't make any sense for most
sports right now I should back up to
this model is just a concept it does not
work for every sport not even close but
it does work for a lot of them
okay so volume goes down throughout the
year it's the highest in the offseason
you're in the gym four or five six times
a week as we're getting a preseason it
starts going down because you're playing
your sport more again when I'm referring
this stuff we're talking about typically
the weight room stuff out the sport as
we get into competition you're really
spending let you're doing less and less
reps in the gym but at the same time
you're going faster you're going heavier
and you're really trying to drive peak
performance as you get to the end of the
competition phase there you have a
really dramatic drop-off in volume and
that allows some super compensation you
should see a nice big spike in
performance so it would look something
like this
okay you may actually see a pretty
decent drop in performance in that
offseason preseason and the reason for
that is volume is really high you're
starting to pick intensity up and you
get a little bit of acute fatigue a
little bit of maybe what we call
functional overreaching so main two or
three weeks go by you Michael numbers to
get worse getting I'm fatigued thanks
for building up don't back off right
then not if you've got a plan not if you
got a year-long structured plan if you
don't know how you're doing you're
making up work ups workouts as you go or
you're making them up every two weeks at
a time well you only look back off
because you know what's going on if
you've got a year built out at least in
concept and you know alright I'm nine
months away this is what I should be
feeling kind of in the pits but I know
soon the volumes coming down I'll start
to recover and perform this will go up
and again look at the very end there you
notice what happens with the yellow bar
as soon as that volume drops off into
the taper and maybe I'll make another
video on taper but as soon as that
happens performance typically jumps way
up and see you Syd's to that big peak
and super compensation the other thing
to note here is this your volume and
intensity doesn't just go up or down
linearly there's small little waves but
those waves are typically offsetting
each other
so week or two when you bump up
intensity a little bit you you have to
go down because volume intensity are
inversely related I can't do more reps
of the same weight off usually or the
inverse you want to go heavier this week
okay well you can take reps down cuz I
get volume you go again
just just as a concept here this is not
exactly how it always works but we're
seeing it there now in a program that I
see if I were grading an assignment I
don't care if your graph looks exactly
like this it just can't be straight
probably straight up or straight down is
okay
some undulations are a little better but
it can't be straight forward there has
to be some sort of progressive overload
right and in order to do that then you
have to reduce volume and so there has
to be some sort of undulation or moving
of that phase so now that you understand
a little bit of how it should work let's
go over some examples okay now there's
two phrases that we use a lot in this
one of them called GPP general physical
performance or simple we will call it
general physical preparation it's super
coaching jargon people slang it all the
time GPP right that's that beginning of
the year stuff right that's that basic
physical conditioning that's volume that
is nonspecific exercises so farmers
carries sled drags general physical
skills jumping throwing squatting
hinging as we get to the end of the
season we move more towards that SST or
sports specific stuff right so now we're
talking about starting in our running
position and technique and where we want
the elbow to be you when we're throwing
those are really specific okay so we
move from GPP early in the year to
sports specific later in the year I want
to make sure we threw those phrases out
there when you go to write your first
cycle whether you're doing a mesocycle
or macro cycle this is what I recommend
and the joke I'm getting out here with
the image is this you're going to want
to start off your program and go okay
open up my computer ok coffee okay
emails turned off word file open save
save document mesocycle for dr. Calvin
scoffs great okay day one
modern-day squats all right he's good
and that's gonna be terrible you know
where this is going right it's gonna be
the worst longest experience you're like
don't do your programs like that save
back squats save front squats next say
all right hit like up more coffee I want
you do the opposite don't smart start
small and work big start big and work
small it's just like how we taught you
to write essays in eighth grade or
whatever the hell that was go for the
biggest concepts first and if you do
that the little things line themselves
up and you just fill in the dots at the
end it's really fast and it's really
well organized let me walk you through
that it's gonna take me a minute here
but let me walk you through exactly how
I think you should do it that will save
you time and we'll end up and result in
better programs so here's the whole
slide you need to go through in detail
this is the exact same thing if you're
only doing a mezzo cycle you can start
with point number six so I'm gonna jump
right there because it's basically the
same thing but number one first you have
to establish what I call a big goal what
are we training for and I can't
especially in a mezzo cycle I can't have
three or four goals two goals is pushing
it I would prefer one I know there may
be other things you go yeah I would also
like to get this but what's the one
thing you have to get in this six eight
ten twelve weeks what does it pick one
thing and be very clear and that needs
to be tangible smart whatever the hell
that I can't stands for specific
measurable attainable realistic and
timely or whatever my point is a number
don't give me a mesocycle goal that says
I want to get stronger no you want to
get stronger in what lift at and what
number I want to add five pounds of my
benchpress got it deal
no I want to get stronger I want my arms
to get bigger you know how much bigger
how are we measuring very specific okay
let's go with the example of um one
improve my benchpress by ten percent
okay fine step number one that's written
down notice I'm not programming any
exercises yeah I'm not even close to
picking exercises I've gotta figure out
what I'm training for first what I'm
writing
second is in identifying my defenders
now go back and watch the needs analysis
video for that but figure out what's
stopping me from bench pressing that
number originally is the strength is it
mobility is it size is hypertrophy is a
conditioning what is it identify that
defender and write that down it may be
one two three four defenders whatever
they all write them down and for each of
those defenders you need to identify a
very specific align even your
assignments I got to see that in your
program you have clearly identified a
goal how many defenders and what are
your specific mini goals within each one
of those things so I want to improve my
bench by five percent my defenders are
shoulder mobility and chest size and
strength and so I'm going to improve my
Peck strength by five percent improve my
internal rotation of my shoulder by an
inch and I will add two inches an inch
to my chest whatever the hell the
numbers are I don't want to care this is
something tangible from there and then
determine how long and what order your
blocks need to be in all right so okay
it's me it's a little bit of flexibility
so I'm gonna do a two-week block on my
shoulder internal rotation while I add
some size and then I'm going to do six
weeks of strength cuz it's mainly a
strength issue okay great
once you determine how important each
one of these things are then you know
how long to make the block and that's
the basic equation the more important it
is the longer you think it's going to
take to achieve give it a longer block
that's it okay so you determine your
block lengths and then you go through
each block and do the same thing what's
the goal of that block what's the
defender of that block what's the
meaning goal and then more and more and
more and more MORE alright just keep
going to that if once you do that
eventually you're gonna have you're
gonna get to a situation where you're
like okay I need to write a one day
program for foot speed easy done okay
tomorrow I have to do a one day program
for leg signs okay I know rep ranges and
intensities for hypertrophy done and it
becomes pretty easy to fill in so I'll
walk you through a very specific example
here you use your own though okay so
step number one is actually the first
thing I do is identify the calendar so
pick the important day 21 vague
holidays exams getting married
hard times the year you can't get to the
gym when your competition days start why
there if you're doing a Meza site or a
macro cycle specifically you gotta plan
this stuff out right if you write the
hardest a three-week training block of
the entire year that falls in somebody
spring break and you know they're going
to Cancun well you're an idiot life will
never win our life will always win sorry
not your training program so write down
all the non-negotiable dates in the
calendar and then work backwards okay
that's actually step number one but then
step number two is get that big gold
down say this is example it's back squat
you want to prove that by 15%
that's our mezda cycle big goal we've
identified two primary defenders leg
strength and ankle flexibility and then
we hade put specific mini goals to each
one of those okay then we decide on our
block length okay and I've walked you
through this orally a second ago but now
you're seeing visuals of it and so your
your entire mesocycle might have a
structure a schematic and it looks
something like this all right
easing it now describe me five weeks of
strength four legs you can do that start
off week one right a strength program
and just progress it a little bit over
five weeks and there should be no
problem all right I'll give you a couple
more scenarios to think through let's
say the mesda cycle goal is weight loss
that's a pretty common one right and it
give you two scenarios scenario one is
the person is you know in shape they
have adequate muscle they're just little
bit overweight what do you think they're
mesocycle would look like just from this
big schematic well let's compare that to
scenario two all right because in this
case you might just go straight the
mesocycle of high intensity conditioning
they're in shape already they move well
they got muscle he's gonna burn some
calories but I have no problem getting
this person to start at day one and
doing eight straight weeks maybe with
week five we back off a little bit to
recover but we kind of go hard hard hard
for three back off three or four weeks
back off then go hard into the internet
no problem there it might look like this
boom don't even need a block really
right
let's go the exact same training goal
weight loss but let's go a different
scenario okay so now the scenario is
they've never exercised before in their
life they have low muscle mass and
they're overweight I would not put this
person straight into a high-intensity
interval week they're gonna get so sore
hurt it's not gonna last me or flame out
you need to actually step back and say
okay your defender or why you're over
weights a little bit different and the
first persons so maybe we need to spend
time in this mesocycle getting ready to
exercise so maybe the design needs to
look something like this maybe two weeks
of flexibility or kind of light body
weight movements then working and maybe
three or four weeks I perch if you just
to build some volume in the joint some
basic strength GPP and then maybe by the
end of the eight weeks we'll start
getting conditioning I promise if you
did somebody like that who has never
exercised they're overweight and then
I'm doing six weeks of hypertrophy
auditioning they're gonna lose weight at
least the exercise parts taken care of
if they don't there's this nutrition
right but this is a realistic approach
to this person because they're their
problems are different and you're not
gonna kill these people
by doing something like that okay so
once we get that done we move on to the
micro-cycles and the micro-cycles are
not that much more complicated so let's
take a look at several different
examples of how I can manipulate the
Micra cycles while having the same exact
mezcla cycle goal now there's pros and
cons to each one of these approaches so
I want you to learn that understand that
and then use the one that is most
appropriate for your situation so for
the example of Lauren or for the purpose
of learning here let's just assume that
in every one of these scenarios the goal
is the same I portrayed okay so riding a
missile cycle to maximize hyper tripping
let me show you four or five different
examples of how you can do that example
one kind of like the fat loss when we
talked about maybe eight to eight weeks
our perch feet done we modulate
progressively overload we go up and down
a little bit with volume with the back
off weight but there's no other training
application example to is what we call
alternating by microcycle or alternating
by week so it could be something like
this two weeks conditioning two weeks I
perch be two weeks of strength two weeks
convert repeat pretty similar to the
other example I just
right but in this particular case notice
how the overall adaptation at the end at
eight weeks the biggest thing we're
gonna get is still hypertrophy why
because that's what we spent the most
time on that's what's going to determine
what our biggest adaptation is right we
didn't need to do the whole thing
because we had other stuff we had to
work on now what's the pro of the week -
well it allows us to work on our the
alternating my micro cycle approach it
allows us to work on multiple things a
downside
well you didn't spend as much time on
our Qi as you did in the example one so
you're not gonna get as much hypertrophy
but you may have needed to invest that
time there because you had bigger
promises all
everything has a pro and con this gets
even a more exacerbated when we go to
example three which is alternating by
day this may be something like day one
of the week is hypertrophy day two of
the week is strength day three of the
weakest hypertrophy same thing as
example1 example2 that's still
hypertrophy mesocycle the end will still
get there but you may have decided for
example we need some strength - so you
wanted to give yourself a very specific
day to either keep the strength that
you've just got done building for eight
weeks or or because you're also really
weak and maybe the next phase the next
muscle cycle is strength so you want to
start building a little bit of strength
working now so it's not a big of a shock
when you get to the next time for
whatever reason my point thing it's
still a hypertrophy block it will still
get you some my per trophy in this
massive cycle for example for that's
called alternating with ending so a lot
of people call this vertical integration
the previous two examples or different
variations of undulating periodization
is what a lot of people call it daily
undulating or weekly undulating
gradation but the vertical integration
approach here would be something like
this every day you train say you're
training three days a week like all the
rest of the examples doesn't matter we
can do a little bit of speed work maybe
one or two speed exercises you do one or
two strength exercises but the most of
your day that every day you workout is
dedicated I per trophy now the advantage
of the all turning within there this
vertical integration approaches you
don't have to go you're eight weeks like
example one without doing any of the
other movements
in other words if you did set example
one or example two of a specific example
one and you only detect perching for
eight weeks you would definitely get a
lot I per trophy but that means you
would go two months without ever going
fast no strength work no power work well
if you're an athlete that may be tough
to do it may suck to spend three months
getting fast and then and not do
anything fast break weeks you're gonna
lose a lot of those games so an approach
like example four allows you to do a
little bit of everything just to keep
those things sharp keep them alive a
little bit but still emphasizing for the
most part I purchase me in this case you
can do the same thing a speedo is your
goal so you do you know 80% of your
workout everyday is speed and then you
finish with just a little bit of
strength a little bit I approach if we
don't change exercise order here but
just change the emphasis how much time
am i spending is really determining now
raw decision and that's the theme for
all of these examples whether it's
within the day every other day within
each week more than the whole block what
determines the overall adaptation is
what you spent the most time working on
all right so that gives us the
flexibility to come up with a couple of
different block design approaches now
design one is your very classic stair up
up up down right so you're seeing here
is the volume load or the amount of work
I do week one goes up we to progressive
overload three and then back off for
this three to one approach is very very
very common most coaches are gonna use
somewhere between three to five weeks of
loading before they have a back off week
I don't think there's any magic to three
to one I like four to one but you get
the idea right up up up up some back off
now what's interesting I like the color
coding here because well look at week
one of every block all the greenish
names notice how if you looked at those
that's all linear right week one of each
block is always heavier than the week
one of the previous one same with week
two same week three and in fact same
with week four even the back off weeks
four and in fact if you look at the back
off week of block for this is sixteen
weeks or four months in a training your
back off week is actually heavier and
harder then your very first week of
training it's actually almost as hard as
your hardest
week a block one it's cuz you're in
better shape now right you're more fit
and so this allows you to continually
progressively overload throughout the
year but not just trying to do more and
more literally every week that's not
going to work maybe it's a very
beginning of your training early in your
training phase but it won't last very
long right so this is a way that you can
develop your mezzo 0 and your blocks and
progressively overload an example of
that would be something like this
imagine we're training for four weeks
right per trophy you may decide okay I'm
going to keep the volume the dispar
simplicity for the first three weeks the
same and I'll go up 5% per week but week
four I'll back off a little bit in
volume sound off week notice look at the
volume mode here it's just a 20 30
percent reduction and so instead of
doing 30 reps per exercise I now take it
out of 16 and I lower the weight a
little bit I'm not going all the way
back down to baseline
I'm going back up something like this is
more than acceptable very effective
program for a lot of people even
high-level people this would work for a
different approach for strength maybe
something like this again where you
slightly improve you probably can't go
up 5% in your intensity for strength
every week so maybe more like 2% is more
appropriate and then a back off week
where we take the volume down just a
little and intensity a little we're
gonna feel it but we should be nice and
refreshed for week 5 which will come
back with which is gonna be heavy and
hard so an example of integrating all of
these things would be something like
this you got a 12-week mesocycle you got
three blocks block one you're doing
about 10 reps percent we're gonna go up
up up week four we back off that's
clearly gonna be a weird a week when
we're working on hyper true for your
conditioning right the next block we
drop way down but now the intensity goes
way up because we're doing five reps per
set this is probably a strength block
something like that we're still
progressing though so week five six
seven back off week eight and then week
ten or back off week nine sorry we tend
we come in probably with the max
strength or a speed or a power we're
doing two or three reps per set I'm
gonna go up up up up up I don't cover so
it's still about three two one thing
we're also integrating now different
blocks
across time all right so your a week ten
week mesocycle sixteen week mesocycles
can follow these basic approaches and
probably be pretty productive well it's
my overall adaptation for that training
program a little bit everything right a
little bit of science a little bit of
strength a little bit of power which is
probably a pretty good thing in most
cases so here's what I recommend right
you've decided the goal of your of your
year your mezzo your block micro cetera
you've also decided your identifiers you
set your mezzo mini goals now what do
you do yeah this is my personal
recommendation for how you fill in the
remaining slots I personally would
recommend picking your periodization or
progressing approach so if you like
daily undulating periodization or you
like the weekly undulating position or
you wanted the vertical integration
decide on that
then choose your frequency how many days
you have to work with you gonna be in
three days a week five days etc choose
your exercises put them in the right
order then program the intensity and the
volume the rest intervals will basically
fill themself I know note
don't forget the respite holes people
always leave that off don't do that that
makes it pretty easy to put together now
all this being said keep a couple of
things in mind what we're talking about
is trying to optimize a program with
people that are incredibly untrained
sometimes they just eliminate this they
just kind of just work out and you're
like well worked for my friend he did
yeah well kind of everything works for
someone who's pretty untrained but that
doesn't mean it's optimal it's not
providing them a base for the future and
it's not the best thing they could have
possibly done so don't disguise working
for best thing right which is a common
mistake alright so hopefully you learn a
little bit more about the foundation of
program design once again I am dr. Andy
Galpin this has been 25-minute
physiology there's a ton more videos
about program design nutrition
physiology neurology everything else you
can imagine
on this youtube page if you enjoyed this
if you learned something please help
spread the good word if not enjoy have a
lovely day do something better with your
program design get stronger get faster
people will like you better girls will
like you better
boys will
like you better and you'll probably make
more money I don't know if any that's
true I don't really care but one loved
one nation thanks we've done
[Music]